Guide to the Matthew Jennett papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Matthew Jennett papers
1883-2011
1940-1989
YCAL MSS 231
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.51
(13 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 4 record album storage
The Matthew Jennett papers contain subject files, sound recordings, and other material documenting the life and work of Matthew Jennett as editor of Pharos Books. The subject files feature correspondence, writings, and printed ephemera relating to publication projects with Pharos Books. There are files for authors, publishers, and designers, including Bob Cato, Franz Douskey, Peter Ganick (of Potes & Poets Press), Leslie Lee, and Jonathan Williams (of the Jargon Society), Patrick Leigh Fermor, among others. Files also contain examples of fine printing by small presses such as the Ives Street Press. Sound recordings collected by Jennett consist of nineteen 78 speed albums containing radio broadcasts dating from the 1940s. There are programs from the National Broadcasting Company (NBC) and the Columbia Workshop, including "Emma Lazarus," from the "Eternal Light Series" held at the Jewish Theological Seminary in New York City, and "They Burned the Books," a radio drama written by Stephen Vincent Benét.
Jennett, Matthew
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Matthew Jennett, 2006-2012.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Boxes 6-9, 17 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Matthew Jennett
Matthew Jennett, former editor of Pharos Books in New Haven, Connecticut, is Curator of Special Collections, Rare Books & Archives, The American College of Greece.
Scope and Contents
The Matthew Jennett papers contain subject files, sound recordings, and other material documenting the life and work of Matthew Jennett as editor of Pharos Books. The subject files feature correspondence, writings, printed ephemera, such as broadside and keepsakes, and other material documenting publication projects with Pharos Books. There are files for authors, publishers, and designers, including Bob Cato, Franz Douskey, Peter Ganick, Leslie Lee, and Jonathan Williams,Patrick Leigh Fermor, among others. Sound recordings collected by Jennett consist of nineteen 78 speed albums containing radio broadcasts dating from the 1940s. There are programs from the National Broadcasting Company (NBC) and the Columbia Workshop, including "Emma Lazarus," from the "Eternal Light Series" held at the Jewish Theological Seminary in New York City, and "They Burned the Books," a radio drama written by Stephen Vincent Benet.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Subject Files, 1883-2000. II. Sound Recordings, 1940-1949. III. Other Material, undated. IV. February 2011 Acquisition, 1925-2010. V. May 2012 Acquisition, 1980-2011.
Acquisitions recieved after the initial gift date were organized by accession. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition may overlap with/or relate to material found in other acquisitions.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Small presses -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1898-1943; Cato, Bob; Douskey, Franz; Ganick, Peter; Jennett, Matthew; Lee, Leslie, 1930-2014; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008; Ives Street Press; Jargon Society; Jewish Theological Seminary of America; National Broadcasting Company; Pharos Books; Potes & Poets Press
- Subject Files, 1883-2000; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Subject Files, features correspondence, writings, printed ephemera, and other material documenting publication projects with Pharos Books. There are files for authors, small presses, publishers, and designers, including Bob Cato, Franz Douskey, Peter Ganick, Leslie Lee, and Jonathan Williams, among others.
  Folders have been preserved in their alphabetical arrangment by personal name. This means that files associated with small presses or publishers are arranged by the individual's last name. Hence, material relating to Potes & Poets Press can be found with Ganick, Peter, and files relating to the Jargon Society can be found with Williams, Jonathan. Cross references are provided where appropriate in the box and folder list below.
  Many files contain mixed contents, with letters, drafts and proofs, financial records, and other material. Writings, when present, are identified in folder notes. Files also contain examples of modern fine printing by small presses such as Ives Street Press.
  - Anthoensen Press
  - Barreiro, Jose, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Butterick, George F., 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes proofs
  - Cash, Barbara, [circa 1923]-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes third-party letters from Lola Ridge, editor of Broom, to "Stephen"
  - Cato, Bob, 1981-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Cowley, Malcolm
  - Curbstone Press
  - Douskey, Franz, 1982-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
    Includes correspondence with Anthoensen Press, Malcolm Cowley, The Ingram Merrill Foundation, and others, as well as drafts for Archeological Nights and other writings
  - ECM (firm), 1981 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes photograph by Roberto Masotti
  - Eshleman, Clayton, 1983 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Faulkner, [Donald] W., 1980-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fife, Darlene, 1986-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    Includes printed version of Fife's Portraits From Memory: New Orleans in the Sixties (Surregional Press) and photographs
  - Flynn, Robert, 1932-, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ganick, Peter, 1982-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    Includes proofs of Ganick's Remove a Concept
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1982 February 4 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Contains copy of "Declaration of Three..."
  - Head, Robert Grady, 1986-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
    Includes drafts of Head's The Green Tree and other poems
  - Holmes, John Clellan, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Includes corrected draft of Holmes' essay "The Huckleberry Party"
  - The Ingram Merrill Foundation
  - Ivy Street Press
  - Jargon Society
  - Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1883 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes printed version of Lamar's speech "The Tariff"
  - Lawless, Gary, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lee, Leslie, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
    Includes drafts:
    "Almos' a Man" (filmscript)
    "Between Now and Then" (playscript)
    "The Book of Lambert" (playscript)
    "Killing Time" (playscript)
  - Lee, Leslie, 1977-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-35)
    "Never the Time and the Place" (novel)
    "Solomon Northup: Twelve Years a Slave" (teleplay)
    "Willie" (playscript)
  - Lehrer, Warren, 1981-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Mizener, Arthur, 1937, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Includes third-party letters relating to William Rose Benet
  - Petroff, Stephen, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Picciotto, Roberto, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    Includes draft of Picciotto's "The Master's Gifts"
  - Picciotto, Roberto, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
  - Potes & Poets Press
  - Raymond, Richard C., undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - [Rodney, Janet], 1989 December (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Scott, Geoffrey, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Contains printed version of Scott's poem "The Death of Shelley"
  - Scully, James, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Shaw, Robert, 1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Includes printed version of Shaw's Private Time, Public Time (1969)
  - Smith, Andre, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Includes printed versions of Smith's Concerning the Education of a Print Collector
  - Taylor, Alexander, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Vostell, Wolf, 1981 May (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Weaselsleeves Press
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1969-1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 51-54)
    Includes photograph
  - Unidentified, 1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Sound Recordings, 1940-1949; Series II; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by program title. Titles taken from external labels.
  Series II, Sound Recordings, consists of nineteen 78 speed albums containing radio broadcasts dating from the 1940s. There are programs from the National Broadcasting Company (NBC) and the Columbia Workshop, including "Emma Lazarus," from the "Eternal Light Series" held at the Jewish Theological Seminary in New York City, and "They Burned the Books," a radio drama written by Stephen Vincent Benet.
  Albums are restricted pending reformatting and may be consulted only with persmission of the appropriate curator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 6-9 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Dear Adolph," Parts One through Six, 1942
  - "Eternal Light, Emma Lazarus," Parts One through Six, 1949 November 13
  - "Nightmare at Noon" and "Radio in the Rain," Parts One through Six, 1940 August 11
  - "They Burned the Books," Parts Two and Six, 1942 May
  - " Toward the Century of Common Man," Part Three, 1942 June 14
  - "Young Book Reviewers" Parts One through Six, 1946 November 16
  - Untitled, undated
- Other Material, undated; Series III
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Other Material, consists of a small number of "miscellaneous" items.
  - List of "Mark Twain Sketches", undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Negative of unidentified man, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Notebook of clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Oversize and Other Storage, 1940-1986; 3.01; (5 boxes)
  - Oversize
    - "Baseball: A Dream of Spring," poem, printed version, photocopy (In Series I), undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Review of "Willie" (In Series I), 1980 August 17 (Box bsd, folder 61)
    - Poster for event signed by Petroff (In Series I), 1981 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Envelope from Picciotto to Jennett (In Series I), 1984 September 11 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Broadsides relating to Jonathan Williams (In Series I), 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Envelopes and box (In Series II), 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Record Album Storage
    - "Dear Adolph," Parts One through Six, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 66-68)
    - "Eternal Light, Emma Lazarus," Parts One through Six, 1949 November 13 (Box 6, Folder 69-71)
    - "Nightmare at Noon" and "Radio in the Rain," Parts One through Six, 1940 August 11 (Box 7, Folder 72-74)
    - "They Burned the Books," Parts Two and Six, 1942 May (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - "Toward the Century of Common Man," Part Three, 1942 June 14 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - "Young Book Reviewers," Parts One through Six, 1946 November 16 (Box 8, Folder 77-79)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 9, Folder 80-84)
- February 2011 Acquisition, 1925-2010; 4; 2.33; (6 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Matthew Jennett, 2011.
  The 2011 addition to the collection includes Jennett's subject files, correspondence, photographs, clippings, collected materials and writings by Jennett as well as others.
  Material has been arranged primarily in the order in which it was received.
  - David Abrahamsen appraisal material, undated (Box 10)
  - John Clellon Holmes appraisal material, correspondence, and reports, 1983-1989, undated; 2 folders (Box 10)
    Includes photocopies of correspondence between John Clellon Holmes and Jack Kerouac.
  - Peter Mass appraisal material, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Alfred Kinsey speech, Columbia University, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with or regarding Nathan F. Leopold, Jr., 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - David Berkowitz correspondence, 1945-1982; 5 folders (Box 10–11)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 11)
  - Pharos Books early ephemera, undated (Box 11)
  - Timothy Verdon CV and artwork photographs, undated (Box 11)
  - Rabe/ F.W. Yves Montana ephemera, clippings, and photographs, 1969 (Box 11)
  - Boston University Ulysses controversy clippings and news releases, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Ever Wonder How She Stole Your Heart Away? script by James Childs, 1996 (Box 11)
  - Mazzoni photographs, undated (Box 12)
  - Printed material featuring writing by Jennett, 1977-2008; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Jazz writings, clippings, and ephemera, circa 1970s-1990s; 5 folders (Box 12–13)
  - Jazz photographs (prints and negatives), undated; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Art and photography reviews by Matthew Jennett, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 13)
  - Book reviews, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 13)
  - I, Antigone Epidavros Festival ephemera, script, 1999 (Box 13)
  - Appraisal of the Janet Camp Troxell collection: photographs, correspondence, and ephemera, 1925-1991 (Box 13)
  - Catalog for the Janet Camp Troxell collection of Rossetti, 1971 (Box 14)
  - New Haven Black Panther trials protest rally photographs (contact sheets and negatives), 1970 (Box 14)
    Includes images of Allen Ginsberg.
  - Yale co-op clippings, 1983-1984 (Box 14)
  - Olson on the Right Track by Fielding Dawson, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Robert Lowell poetry and clippings, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Theodoros Stamos clippings, correspondence, and interview transcript, 1974-2004 (Box 14)
  - Harry Mark Petrakis, 1969-2005 (Box 14)
  - Raymond Roseliep poetry and correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
  - Robert Penn Warren correspondence, 1973-1981 (Box 14)
  - Elsa Sparioti writings, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 14)
  - Michael Rumaker correspondence, inventories, and biographical material, 1983-1990 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence of Janet Camp Troxell, 1951-1975 (Box 15)
    Includes a manuscript of Queen Victoria's family tree
  - Miscellaneous writings, 2010, undated (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous writings, correspondence, and printed materials, 1926-2005 (Box 15)
- May 2012 Acquisition, 1980-2011; 5; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Gift of Matthew Jennett, 2012.
  The 2012 addition to the collection includes material relating to British author, Patrick Leigh Fermor. Material includes Jennett's correspondence with Fermor, writings by Fermor, and photographs of Fermor taken by Jennett.
  - Patrick Leigh Fermor correspondence and photographs, circa 1990s-2011 (Box 16)
  - Manuscript and proofs of George Psychoundakis: A Letter to C.A. Trypanis by Patrick Leigh Fermor, 1980; 1996 (Box 16)
  - Patrick Leigh Fermor writings, booklets, and clippings, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 16)
  - Envelope previously containing Reichian Therapy and the Orgone Accumulator, undated (Box 16)
    Separated Materials
    Audiocassette removed for separate housing.
    - Reichian Therapy and the Orgone Accumulator, 1981; 1 (Box 17)
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.